<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Brief relation of several passages of the life and death of William Barton of Shrewsbury, in October, 1661 wherein may be seen much wickedness against great workings of God in him, as also God's most just anger, and wondrous mercy (as is hoped) towards him / published by a relation of his, and intended chiefly for the good of such as knew him in Shrewsbury, many of whom can testify the truth of these things.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37471</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16960602</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16960602</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105482</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105482)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1610:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Brief relation of several passages of the life and death of William Barton of Shrewsbury, in October, 1661 wherein may be seen much wickedness against great workings of God in him, as also God's most just anger, and wondrous mercy (as is hoped) towards him / published by a relation of his, and intended chiefly for the good of such as knew him in Shrewsbury, many of whom can testify the truth of these things.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Allen ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Barton, William, d. 1661.</term>
               <term>Repentance.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105482:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF RELATION Of ſeveral Paſſages of the LIFE and DEATH OF WILLIAM BARTON OF <hi>SHREWSBURY,</hi> In <hi>October,</hi> 1661.</p>
            <p>Wherein may be ſeen much Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt great Workings of God in him; As alſo God's moſt juſt Anger, and wondrous Mercy (as is hoped) towards him.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by a Relation of his, and intended chiefly for the good of ſuch as knew him in <hi>Shrewsbury:</hi> many of whom can teſtify the truth of theſe things.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Stand in awe, and ſin not.</l>
               <l>Behold the goodneſs and ſeverity of God.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Allen,</hi> at the Riſing Sun in <hi>Little Brittain,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105482:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105482:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce it was the earneſt deſire of my poor unworthy Brother, whom notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (we hope) God was graciouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to own and love, to honour God ſome way, to ſhame Sin, and to betray the deceits of the Devil, that God's hand upon him might do good to ſome. Since this was his deſire, and ſhould be the endeavour and deſign of all thoſe that love God, I have therefore, by the advice of ſome Friends, thought fit to preſent unto your conſideration ſeveral Paſſages, which through the bleſſing of God may tend thereunto. The Method of this Diſcourſe you muſt not expect to be orderly, being penned by one that is unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in ſuch work. If therefore you ſhall think any of the Paſſages therein impertinent, or rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought in, impute it not to him of whom the Diſcourſe is, but rather unto the unskilfulneſs of the Penner, in ordering of it: For ſure I am, for my own part, I never did ſee any man more ſenſibly appear to be affected with what he ſpake, than he was during the time of this his viſitation which was about the ſpace of ſeven weeks: And
<pb facs="tcp:105482:3"/>although his Speeches, and thoſe Paſſages which have relation to this Providence, as they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by me, may not affect you, yet ſure I am, if you had ſeen that ſeriouſneſs, deep ſence and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table affections, which accompanied thoſe paſſages in him, you could not but have been affected therewith. Many choice things (judged per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by divers to be better than theſe) were ſpoke by him at ſeveral times, which I am not able to ſet down. I have given you, as near as I could, his own words, omitting, as much as I thought I might, the diſcourſe of others which occaſioned them; And although but very briefly and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenly on my part, yet I hope out of this confuſed heap, you may pick ſomething which may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other do you good: for which hope-ſake I am encouraged to publiſh the ſame, although I often feared, and do fear that I ſhall thereby purchaſe the ſcorns of ſome: yet knowing that wiſe men will take that well which was well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, paſſing by ſmall faults; or, with the Bee, gather Honey, though from a Weed, I am thereby encouraged, and muſt venture the displeaſure of others.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105482:3"/>
            <head>A brief Relation of ſeveral Paſſages of the Life and Death of <hi>William Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FIrſt, let me beg your patience whilſt I give you a deſcription of his Diſpoſition &amp; manner of Life, to the end you may the better judge of the whole Diſcourſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He was a Young Man, not above twenty eight years of age, born and educated in the Town of</hi> Shrewsbury, <hi>of honeſt Parents; the Trade he followed was a Butcher. He was from a Child well educated; he learned ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chapters &amp; Pſalms in the Bible by heart; from a Child would remember much of a Sermon, and would often be teaching thoſe brothers and ſiſters of his, who were young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than himſelf; ſeemed the hopefulleſt and the forwardeſt to good, of any of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and very forward to teach others: Yet in one thing he was many times faulty from a Child, which was, a great aptneſs to ſpeak lies, uſually hiding his fault by a lye, for fear of puniſhment, and was much given to talk and brag.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105482:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>He was one that would take a great deal of pains in his Calling, and was very diligent in whatſoever he went about: He was alſo of a loving and pittiful diſpoſition, very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to forgive any injury, even to his greateſt enemies; very pittiful and charitable to the poor, for many times he would give (though he had but little in the houſe) very freely to them: When he had but half a loaf in his houſe, ſeeing a poor woman go by, his heart pittied her, and he called her back, and gave her half of it: He was very glad to ſee others good, and rejoyced when he ſaw reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in any that had been formerly more looſe. When he was told that one in the Town that had been very looſe, was become a changed man, and followed that which was good, he wept for joy, and ſaid,</hi> Methinks I feel my heart love him; <hi>nay, he would often weep for joy at the good he heard or ſaw in others, eſpecially in his relations. He would give very good counſel to any he thought needed it, although he loſt their love by it, and though he himſelf did follow it but poorly, being too much the ſervant of ſin. He had alwayes a love to good Miniſters, and he would often ſay that he would venture his life for them; Yet he was many times a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of vain perſons, ſpending his time with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105482:4"/>them in the Alehouſe; yet among them, as occaſion was given, he would ſpeak for God and his People, ſo that it was obſerved that he had not their love, with whom he ſpent ſo much of his time and money. He was much given to vain glory, ſo that a little praiſe, or expreſſion of love, would win his heart, and eaſily draw him any way: yet he oft-times loved to reade, and uſed to pray in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and ſometimes in ſecret, though, as he after complained, very ſeldom. Oft-times (after he had broken out) he would be very ſad, from the conſideration of his life, and as he confeſſed afterwards, his ſins ſeemed ſo horrible to him that they almoſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed him, and would make him think there was no hope for him, ſo that he was fain to ſtifle all thoſe workings, and buſſle through them with ſome kind of hope of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, yet at ſuch times he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the cauſe of his trouble. After, upon ſome diſcontent with his wife, and through the poverty which he had brought upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his evil courſes, he went into</hi> Scotland, <hi>where it pleaſed God to viſit him with a great fit of ſickneſs, and to lay before him his life in ſuch a manner, as was horrible to him; ſo that when he looked back upon his wayes, he was even overwhelmed; but when he looked
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105482:5"/>forward, he ſaw ſome hope, and was full of reſolutions of a new life; and when he was recovered, he lived in a ſtricter manner for a while, and found much comfort and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from God, and ſuch ſweetneſs in that ſhort time of obedience and reſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, as he never had found in any thing in the world; yet after his returning into</hi> England <hi>he grew to the ſame paſs again, lived after the ſame rate, and was in many things worſe, and ran into ſome ſins he had never committed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, By his evil wayes, as gaming, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany-keeping, he grew in debt, and alwayes for the ſpace of the laſt half-year was in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of arreſting. He would often defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from them with threatning words, ſuch as theſe:</hi> Keep off me, you know not what I may do; do not come near me, leſt I ſet you to ſleep with your fathers, <hi>having often his knife in his hand. Theſe and ſuch words he ſpake with as daunting a carriage as he could, and by this means he kept himſelf almoſt the ſpace of half a year out of their hands, abſenting himſelf alſo ſometimes out of the Town, and taking ſuch courſes as he ought not. But one time above all, being full of drink, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs (as at ſuch times he uſed to be) a young man who was an Apprentice to an Officer in the Town, who had a great hatred to him, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105482:5"/>had often threatned to take him either dead or alive, (which the ſaid</hi> William Barton <hi>knew not of, until it was proved at his tryal) This young man came one morning, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with another, ſeeking to take him; but at that time, he having his knife in his hand, and ſpeaking great words, kept himſelf out of their hands: yet in the evening the young man watching for him about the houſe, came running upon him as he ſtood at his Mothers Shop, and he having his knife in his hand, the man holding him by the back (for he turned himſelf to go in) he ſtruck his hand behind him, which went ſtreight upon the man's heart, ſo that he run but about thirty yards, crying,</hi> Stop him, he hath mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered me, <hi>and ſo fell down and dyed: And he being taken, would not believe he had hurt the man, but that they intended to afright him. About an hour before, he was counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by one of his friends, not to threaten, or to draw his knife, leſt God ſhould leave him to himſelf, to do that which he intended not to do. His anſwer was;</hi> I will hurt no body I'le warrant you; let me alone; Do you think I have no care of my ſelf? <hi>But he was never the ſafer for all his ſelf-confidence. He had been more faſe if he had feared more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being put into Priſon, he was ſo full of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105482:6"/>drink, that immediately he ſlept very ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a time; but coming to him the next morning, we found him mightily awakened with the apprehenſion of his guilt, and of God's ſeverity againſt ſin, with a dejected countenance full of horrour and tears, thus he ſaid:</hi> O the blood of this poor innocent man, which I have ſent away in his ſins! I am afraid his blood cryes againſt me, it lies at my heart, here it lies, it cannot be waſh'd away: O no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is before me but guilt, and an angry God, and Death and Hell, who ſhall dwell with ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting burnings! <hi>This Scripture terrified him often,</hi> Becauſe I have called, and ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, I will laugh at your calamity, and mock when your fear cometh: but I will juſtifie God, though it be to my deſtruction: he hath not been wanting to me, but I have been wanting to my ſelf: mine own iniquity hath taken me, and I am held in the cords of mine own ſin. O pray for me, every one that hath an intereſt in God; pray for me, for I cannot pray for my ſelf: my mouth is ſtop'd, my works ſink me. <hi>Thus he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed full of horror, crying out becauſe of the innocent blood that was ſhed by his hand; and multiplying Scriptures againſt himſelf, theſe and ſuch like:</hi> He that being often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and hardeneth his neck, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed and that without remedy. Wo be to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105482:6"/>wicked, it ſhall be ill with him, for the reward of his hands ſhall be given him, he ſhall eat of the fruit of his own wayes, and be filled with his own devices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>On the ſecond day ſome of his relations coming to him, found him lying upon the ſtraw, and, as formerly, crying out becauſe of the guilt and horrour of his ſin. His firſt words to his relations were,</hi> Am I not caſt out of your hearts? <hi>who told him that he was not, foraſmuch as he was yet alive; and there was ſome hopes, for there is an earneſt ſpirit of prayer upon many good people that know you, and that hear of you; and they told him alſo, that his Siſter</hi> Mary <hi>on her Death-bed, ſpake theſe words to the honour of God, and to encourage us to ſeek,</hi> That ſhe never did earneſtly beg any thing of God, which ſhe could or durſt pray abſolutely for, that ſhe was denied: <hi>and ſhe further ſaid,</hi> That ſhe had ſome hope concerning <hi>William,</hi> that poor Lad, that there are ſome prayers put up for him that will not be denyed.</p>
            <p>But did ſhe ſay ſo <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> O now I have ſome hope: I thought I had been quite out of her heart, that I was bound as to her, but I was not. O ſet all the Town to pray for me; every one that hath any intereſt in God. When I come to pray I dare not, my mouth is ſtopt, I have hid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105482:7"/>my ſins with lying, and I was hypocritical: O I have deceived my ſelf. I dare not look behind me, for my works ſink me into Hell, and I can ſee nothing before me but an angry God, and Death and Hell, and Eternity. O for one ſmile from Heaven; one ſmile from Heaven would be worth all: One drop of Faith and true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is worth all the world. Now come unto me over theſe mountains, and over theſe hills. It were juſt with God that I ſhould have the hope of the Hypocrite, but O that it might not be ſo. I have no hope, but that I am yet out of Hell. A living Dog is better than a dead Lion. O every one that ſees me, take heed of ſin. This is the condition that ſin hath brought me into: now I muſt receive my wages: this is my due wages, I have been working for it all my life. O poor Brother <hi>Thomas,</hi> walk ſoftly in the world, do not be too buſie in it: my Companions cannot deliver me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One of the Beholders that ſtood by, told him that Gods mercy is above all his works, and that in the midſt of judgment he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers mercy; and he hath done ſo to you; for you might have been ſuddenly ſnatcht away, as this poor man that is gone. Then ſaid he,</hi> I can ſee it to be a mercy, for then I had been ſure in Hell, deep in Hell; and I have ſeen mercy in God's dealing to me formerly, in that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105482:7"/>my way was hedged up, and that I did not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in my evil way as others did; and when I ſought the favour of men, and ſhould have ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten down contented with it, I alwayes loſt it: for if I ſhould but have been well thought of in the world, and have had the favour of men, I ſhould never have looked further: But Oh if I ſhould waken thus as I am now, in another world, I were utterly undone, all this would but tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment me. I have a great work to do, and I know not which way to begin; I can do nothing towards it, and I have but a little time: O thou Son of <hi>David,</hi> have mercy on me: O thou Son of <hi>David,</hi> look back and pitty me, I would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee and cry after thee, O that I might not be ſtopt; I would not let thee alone till thou bleſs me: Hear the Prayers that are put up for me; Let the Blood of Chriſt that ſpeaks better things than the Blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> out-cry the cry of my ſins: Pray for me <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> that God would not give me into the Devils hands this night, nor let him come to me; God juſtly might: But pray for me, your prayers may do me good, it may be God will hear your prayers for me: O that ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity might not be my ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Coming to him the third day, and menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning ſome Scriptures unto him, which make known God's good will towards men, and his readineſs to forgive, he anſwered thus:</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105482:8"/>I do believe that if I did hate my ſin as it is ſin, and is againſt God, that I ſhould be forgiven; but I am afraid that I do not hate ſin as it is ſin, and is againſt God; for I do not ſee the reſt of the ſins of my life as I do this; this I can ſee to be horrible and filthy, and it lies heavy upon me; whether it be becauſe this is more odious in the ſight of the world, or whether it be becauſe this makes me lyable to puniſhment from men, or brings me to open ſhame, I cannot tell whether this may be the cauſe; but the reſt of my ſins I cannot feel ſtick ſo upon me, as this doth, and they ſhould; for when I think of their aggravations, they are as bad or worſe; and therefore I am afraid I do not hate ſin as it is againſt God. But how ſhould I do that I may ſee the reſt of my ſins as they be; ſhould I not confeſs all thoſe ſins which I have hid; I think I ſhould; and I ſee the truth of that, He that hideth his ſins ſhall not proſper. <hi>His friends there preſent, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged him to go on with his purpoſe in making an ingenious confeſſion without any hiding or ſparing of himſelf, and that he would be ſure, when he ſhould meet with any hiding or ſparing of himſelf, and that he would be ſure, when he ſhould meet with any ſecret temptation to hide or leſſen any ſin, 02 that he would be ſure to thwart that tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by making a fuller confeſſion of every circumſtance and aggravation thereof, that ſo he might ſhame himſelf the more, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105482:8"/>that deceitful heart that otherwiſe would betray him: And we do believe by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious confeſtions, that he followed this reſolution of his, in confeſſing all, and not hiding any thing, though it might tend much to further his ſhame: And when Children or others ſtood to gaze on him, and were about to be hindered by the Keeper of the Door or others, he would intreat that they might not, ſaying,</hi> Let them alone to look upon me, and ſee the fruits of ſin; <hi>and would put forth his legs to ſhew them his Chains, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Children, it is ſin that hath bound me with theſe Chains, mine own iniquity hath taken me; hearken to the good counſel of your Parents; I began with runing from counſel, and now it hath brought me to this; and ſpake the truth always; when I had done evil, I would think to hide it by lying, and now God hath diſcovered me; I hid my ſins, and therefore I did not proſper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another time ſome of his relations and neighbours coming to him, and after much diſcourſe, which was ſavory from him, he burſt out into extream tears, and ſaid,</hi> O I lye under an hard heart; and if it be hard now I am undone for ever; ſin hath hardened my heart. <hi>The company then going forth of the 100m, thus he ſpake,</hi> Dear Neighbours, this one thing I would have you do, whenever you
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105482:9"/>commit any ſin that you know of, go and confeſs it quickly to God, and to ſome faithful friend, and pray them to pray for you, that your ſin may be forgiven; for I went on in ſin unconfeſt and unforgiven, till I was as full of ſin as I could hold, and then this brake out, and now all my ſin is become a debt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And coming to him the next day, and finding him very ſad and comfortleſs, even quite without hope, we ſought to comfort him, but could not, for thus he cryed out,</hi> God's Word is againſt me; I can ſcarce turn to any place but it is againſt me; my works are againſt me; I am thy works, and I will follow thee: O if my works follow me, I am undone; Ah ſhall lying follow me, and cozening follow me, and diſſembling follow me, and blood follow me: Ah I am afraid there is no hope; but I will hope againſt hope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thus he ſpake to his mother and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations then by;</hi> Dear Mother, what a Son have I been to you, my dear Mother, what a Son have I been to you! what a brother have I been to you all! but mother, they are not all ſuch as I; you have ſome good Children, be thankful for thoſe; they might have been all ſuch as I. <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little ſilence he began again to cry out;</hi> O that I could honour God ſome way before I go out of the world! What a ſcandal have I been to Religion? What a ſavour ſhall I leave behind
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105482:9"/>me? Ah! what an example have I given in the world; O that I might live to give a better exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; I would fain live that I might be an enemy to ſin: O that poor ſouls might not be taken in thoſe ſnares that I have been taken in. Methinks I would not live if I ſhould live as I have done; I would rather dye now, than live to diſhonour God again; If I ſhould live, I would not live as I have done, ſure I ſhould not, methinks I ſhould not: I think I ſhould ſcarce get time, to get my dayly bread, but that I muſt, for it were my duty; but if I ſhould again live as I have done, methinks Hell it ſelf would be too narrow for me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One of his Acquaintance which he had ſpent much time with, came to ſee him;</hi> Ah <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> you and I have cauſe to be humbled for the precious time that we have ſpent together vainly and ſinfully; you may be an honeſt woman for ought I know, but you have cauſe to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, I have I am ſure, yea and you too; Spend no more time as you ſpent it with me: Oh the ſin that accompanied our miſpending of time! Ask God forgiveneſs, and take heed of ſin, you have time yet. Some mens ſins go before to judgment, and ſome mens follow after; I am pickt out to be made an example that you might take heed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another time ſome of his Friends coming and finding him bemoaning himſelf becauſe of ſin, they began to comfort him, and told
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105482:10"/>him, that they did hope and believe, that this was the way that God would make uſe of to bring him home to himſelf, by making him a true penitent; and ſince it hath pleaſed God to give you thus much time, we do hope he will hear the Prayers that are and have been put up for you,</hi> For he never ſaid to the Seed of Jacob, ſeek ye my face in vain, <hi>and you have been a Son of many Prayers.</hi> Never, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> ſeek ye me in vain; Never <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> nay, then not in this condition: Bleſſed be his Name, if this be thy way, for ever bleſſed be thy Name; this is a ſtrange way, muſt I go through Hell to Heaven? But O if this be the way, bleſſed be God; my tongue ſhall ſing aloud of his Righteouſneſs, though it ſhould be upon a Gallows; wonderful Mercy to me, to ſuch a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Creature as me: if this ſhall be the way, then he hath puniſhed me leſs then mine iniquities de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another time ſome of his Neighbours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, he began to confeſs his own guilt, and that he was hypocritical, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to himſelf, and that he ſought the favour of men; nay, and that ſometimes he had not ſtuck at a lye, when he thought it might fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that deſign. Some of the company then by, ſaid,</hi> William, you were not ſo bad as you make your ſelf now, nor ſo bad an hypocrite as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105482:10"/>you think you are, for of our knowledge, you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes loved the beſt People, and loved the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and would take their part, though you were hated for it, and heard Gods Word conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and would remember a great deal of it, and loved to read good, Books, and therefore you were not ſo bad as you make your ſelf to be. All this <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> doth but aggravate my ſins, I did but enough to leave me inexcuſable, and make againſt me; and that you may not be taken in the ſame ſnares that I have been taken in, I will make a relation of my condition; I did delight to hear good Sermons, and longed for the Sabbath-day, and loved it when it did come, And when thoſe Pſalms were ſung that were promiſes to the Saints, that they ſhould be ſatisfied with the fatneſs of God's Houſe, and filled with the Rivers of Delight, and ſuch Pſalms as ſet out the amiableneſs of Gods Tabernacle, and that Scripture where it is ſaid, <hi>The work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be peace, and the effect quietneſs and aſſurance for ever,</hi> I ſhould be much affected, and could not but weep, when I ſung ſuch places: and when my conſcience told me that I was not right, and that my works were naught, and that if I went on as I did, it would be ſad with me, it would make me very ſad, and I would then reſolve that I would be otherwiſe; I would verily think that I ſhould be better, and would reſolve as well
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105482:11"/>(I thought) as any one could reſolve, but when Munday came, and thoſe thoughts were gone of me, I ſhould make little or nothing of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer promiſe, but ſhould break through all as if I had never reſolved; and if any one did but call me, I had no power but to go, and if any thought ſhould come in my mind that might hinder me, I would do the beſt I could to hinder ſuch a thought, becauſe I had a mind to go; and ſometimes I have ſought temptations, and though my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and God's Word, would keep me a great while, yet at the laſt I ſhoul'd break through all, and ſo I loved a little Ale better than God, and better than my ſelf; and when I had broken my reſolutions time after time, I had no heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, and thought it was to no purpoſe, and then I went on without any gage; but I found that when I did reſolve, it was better then when I did not, for ſometimes it would keep me; but when I reſolved not, then I was drove any way; And I would think ſometimes what might be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that my reſolutions never held me as well as other people; others I could ſee, could reſolve and keep their reſolutions, and I alwayes broke mine; and I do think that the cauſe was, that there was ſomething left behind, ſomething there was that my conſcience put me on to do, that I would not do; ſin lay in the bottom hid, and unconfeſt, and I would not go through the ſhame of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105482:11"/>confeſſing that: and though I reſolved againſt every ſin, yet alas that I would never reſolve on; and ſo the ſin of hiding my ſin, was left behind; and now I can ſee that the firſt thing that I ſhould have done, ſhould have been to have confeſt thoſe ſins, which I had kept cloſe all my life, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not part with that, therefore all my reſolutions were as good as nothing; for that ſin which cauſed me to leave out that, cauſed me to break over all my promiſes. Another cauſe was, becauſe I neglected ſecret prayer; and that ſin kept me from praying, and ſtopt my prayers; I could not ask God for ſtrength to do what I could not, becauſe ſin lay hid in my heart, which I ſhould have diſcovered, and I would not. I hid my ſin by lying, and many a time when my mother would ask me what I had ſpent, I have ſaid, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed mother but two pence, when I had ſpent a great deal more; and though I thought I would be better for the time to come, yet I had no power: the ſame evil that kept me from diſcovering that ſin, made me ſtill run further into ſin: Therefore let every one ſpeak alwayes truth, and that which is in their heart, and if they ſhall at any time chance to ſpeak that which is not ſo, let them go and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do it the firſt thing that they do, and tell them that they ſpake that which was not truth; and then go quickly and beg of God to forgive you, and then you will have more power over your
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105482:12"/>ſelf at another time; for if I could but have parted with that one ſin, I do think that I ſhould have had power over the reſt; and I have thought ſo then, and have been convinced that that muſt be done before I ſhould have any more power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, and yet I would never be willing to it; When I would think of going about it, the matter was ſo bad, and I thought I ſhould appear to be ſo odious, that no one would abide me: and then I thought of ſome good folks that did love me, and I thought that they did not love me, but becauſe they thought me to be pretty good, and for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what good in me; and I would think, that if they ſhould know what an one I was, they would never abide me again; and ſuch reaſons as theſe, or ſomething or other, ſtill kept me off; And ſometimes I would put it off with reaſoning, that it was not neceſſary to confeſs it to men, if I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it to God, I thought it would ſerve the turn. Thus I went on runing out of one ſin into another, till I was as full of ſin as I could hold, till I was become all ſin: and I did think that my ſins were even ripe, aud that ſome great thing muſt befal me ſome way or other very ſhortly; and when I thought of what I deſerved, I was afraid it would be ſome great judgement; and for about a month or ſix weeks before this brake out, I had no power to read Gods Word, but when I would take the Bible, thinking to read, I would turn it and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105482:12"/>turn it, and methoughts I would fain find ſome new thing; nothing would ſerve but ſomething that was new; I could begin to read no where, but it was that which I knew before; I thought I knew it all already, and ſo I would lay it down and never read: therefore when you have no mind to read God's Word, and no mind to pray ſecretly, then be ſure the Devil hath you in a great ſnare; take heed, for if the Devil keep you in that ſnare, you cannot reſt there, but will be hurried further into ſin: if you will give way to that one ſin, you cannot ſtay long there, but will be like a troubled Sea, ſtill caſting forth mire and dirt: And ſo it was with me, for I could not ſtop where I would, though I fain would at many things which I have done. That which at the firſt thought hath appeared ſo odious unto me, that I could not abide to think of it, yet I have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſted, till I have been hurried to that very ſin; and I have ſometimes afterwards wondred at my ſelf, how I could ever be brought to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch wickedneſs, and have hated my ſelf for it, and hated that ſin worſe then than ever, and could not reſt, or have any quietneſs in my condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till I had fallen down before God to ask for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs; and yet after a while, by running in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of that ſin, I have been taken in that very ſnare, to commit that ſame ſin, which a little before I have thought, I could never have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105482:13"/>been driven to. I thought I could ſtop where I would, but I could not: How true is that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, where it is ſaid, that <hi>the wicked are like a troubled Sea,</hi> which cannot reſt, but is ſtill <hi>caſting forth mire and dirt.</hi> One reaſon which the Devil (transforming himſelf into an Angel of Light) ſought to hinder and deceive him by, was by putting into his mind, that if he that had profeſſed Religion, ſhould be known to be ſuch a liar, and ſo bad, it would be a great diſcredit to Religion, and wicked men would think that if all Profeſſors were known, they were all ſuch; and this, <hi>he ſaid,</hi> was one reaſon that kept him back, <hi>and I had like to have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, but rather than I would omit it I have brought it in here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>One thing that I heard him ſpeak before his Tryal; When one was counſelling him not to be earneſtly ſet for life, for he was like to find as little favour from men as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt any, he was a man ſo much hated by many, yet that he and they were in the hands of God. Thus he anſwered;</hi> It often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts me that I am in the hands of God: When I look upon my ſelf as in the hands of men it ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies me, and makes me reſtleſs; but when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I am in the hands of God, that quiets me; and when I think they ſhall do nothing but that which God will have done: for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105482:13"/>if God would not have me live, I would not deſire to live; and if he will have me live, he can turn their hearts contrary to their purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and this quiets my heart. I think ſometimes if I ſhould live, it may be ſin would be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, if God ſhould not manifeſt his diſpleaſure againſt ſin, by not letting me live; therefore I know not what to pray for in this matter, I know not what I would have, but I would have God to give me that which he ſees beſt for me. <hi>After a little ſilence his eyes began to fill with tears, and he burſt out with theſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> O I muſt be puniſhed for my ſin, I muſt be puniſhed more than this. This is not a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I have not been puniſhed enough yet, I muſt not think to eſcape thus, I do expect nothing but death: But O if I could honour God before I go out of this world, I would not care, but be willing to dye. <hi>Theſe words came from him, accompanied with much weeping. And he further ſaid:</hi> God gave me a pittiful dispoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but I marred it, and was cruel with it. I have been cruel to Horſes, in making them do more than they were able; and cruel I have been to Men; when I have borrowed money, I have not been careful to pay it again as I was to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row it. O how like <hi>Judas</hi> have I dealt with ſome, when I have given them fair words! God gave me knowledge and parts, and a fine dispoſition,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105482:14"/>that I might do good, and I have turned all the wrong way: O! how unkindly have I dealt with God: that which he gave me in mercy, I have provoked him with, and ſinned againſt him with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When he came to his Tryal, being asked after the Indictment was read, Whether guilty, or not guilty? he anſwered,</hi> Not guilty of Wilful Murder; for (as in the preſence of God I ſpeak it) I had no more intention or thoughts to kill him, than I had to kill my own Brother; whatever words I might ſpeak it was with an intention to keep them from taking me, becauſe I was a poor man, and had nothing to pay, thinking that if I went to priſon I ſhould never get out; but I never had any intention or thoughts to kill him: <hi>but it was carried againſt him; it was the will of God that ſo it ſhould be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>After the Sentence was given, and he brought to the Jaylors houſe, his Mother went to ſee him, but not being admitted, ſhe ſpake unto him through the door, and he told her that he</hi> was more compoſed in his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and better reſolved than he had been a great while, <hi>and ſaid,</hi> It is God's Will that is done, and I would have you all to be chearful, for I hope that I ſhall find <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> a ſufficient Saviour to me; I can have none other hope:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105482:14"/>my ſins ſtick a little heavily ſometimes, but I hope I ſhall get above them; I have hope becauſe of Gods own goodneſs, that <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> will be a ſufficient Saviour to me, I can have none other hope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At another time, his Brother and Siſter being with him, he began to juſtifie God in taking him away, and was clear in owning God's Juſtice and the truth of his Word: Yet as to ſome men he ſaid he was not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied concerning their dealings, though he had ſought in his thoughts to juſtifie them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond day after he was condemned, as he lay upon a Bed, in the night, in his chamber, he was much refreſhed and chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, through a very ſenſible dream, wherein theſe words were very plainly, and ſenſibly as might be, ſpoken to him:</hi> Awake thou that ſleepeſt; and ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee life: <hi>and being awaked, he began to be much affected with thoſe words which were ſo plainly ſpoken to him; and as he rehearſed them to me, and ſeveral others, theſe were his thoughts upon them:</hi> [Awake thou that ſleepest.] <hi>This is ſure ſpoken to me thought he,</hi> Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead; <hi>I was ſleeping upon the very brink of eternity, and have been ſleeping in ſin for a long time, and now Chriſt awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105482:15"/>me; this is a call from Chriſt: and I did believe that the reſt was ſaid to me,</hi> [and he ſhall give thee life.] <hi>And theſe and ſuch like thoughts of Chriſt made my heart yearn with dear thoughts of Chriſt, and thankful thoughts for Chriſt: and I longed to pray, and was earneſtly ſtirred up to prayer, and never longed ſo to pray as I did then; ſo up I got off the Bed I was lying on, and there I fell down upon my knees before God, and me-thought then I felt my heart grow ſofter: it was hard before; I could ſcarce tell what I ſhould pray for, or how; But O then, I found a freeneſs, a fountain of tears came then, it was a call from God; I was ſure then that it was ſo: and when I would have called to mind whereabout this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould be, or where I might find it, I could not remember that ever I had read it, nor knew whereabout to find it: but I was ſure it was the Word of God, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in the Bible, and that I had heard it ſometimes. I do believe that it was a call from God, for I found my heart ſofter then. O now pray, if ever, dear friends, but two dayes now, and no more prayers will be heard for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He was for the moſt part after this time pretty well compoſed in his mind, and had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105482:15"/>a pretty good meaſure of chearfulneſs; not without hope, though full of the ſence of his guilt, grieving much for his ſin, and that he had dealt ſo unkindly with God. And to moſt of the company that came in, he ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to order his ſpeech with as much wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as he could, ſhewing much affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, with an earneſt deſire of their good. And thus he would expreſs himſelf;</hi> O that you would not be taken in thoſe ſnares that I have been taken in! <hi>And this was ſome counſel that ſcarce any could go without,</hi> That they would be ſure alwayes to ſpeak the truth, and that which was in their hearts; and if at any time you ſhall have ſpoken that which you think was not ſo, go quickly and unſay it; ſay, I ſpake that which was not truth; and do not ſtick at ſhame, for I was often hindred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: do not reſt till you have confeſſed it to God, and to ſome faithful friends, and pray them to pray for you, that ſo it might be forgiven you: and ſo you might have more power againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time: And do not delay, but go quickly, whilſt your conſcience puts you upon it; for if you delay, it is very likely you will be hindred and never do it, though you put it off, thinking to do it another time: for when that time came wherein I purpoſed to do it, I had leſs power and leſs heart.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:105482:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>At another time his Siſter-in-law coming to ſee him, thus he expreſſed his affection, with a ſmiling countenance, and tears:</hi> My dear Siſter, my poor Siſter, my heart yerns upon you: I did not love you, becauſe I thought you did not love me, but I did ill: But O now it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with me; for now I love you, I would fain have you better for that which hath befallen me: Oh! that ſince God is now diſtributing his mercy, every one might have ſome, and you might have ſome. Some who have come to me, are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd by that which hath befallen me, &amp; it makes me glad when I think that others will be afraid of ſin, and bettered by this which is befallen me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When his Links were in the knocking of, and he was hurt thereby; thus he ſaid,</hi> I will bear the Indignation of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned againſt him: Thou art juſt, and I have ſinned; why ſhould the living man complain, a man for the puniſhment of his ſin? O the Juſtice of God, he will not let ſin go unpuniſhed. O do not this abominable ſin that Gods ſoul h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes. If thy children tranſgreſs thy Laws, thou wilt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit their ſin with the rod, and their iniquity with ſtripes; but his loving-kindneſs will he not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly take from them, nor alter the thing that hath gone out of his mouth. <hi>Theſe, with many other expreſſions he often uſed alſo at other times. His countenance growing more and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105482:16"/>more chearful, and being in ſuch an extaſie of joy, as though his body could not then have contained his ſoul, theſe were ſome of the expreſſions he then uttered;</hi> Siſter, I do verily believe that I am now going to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; all thoſe clouds that were upon me are all blown away, his own Arm hath brought Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: He is my Glory, my Deliverer, in Him will I truſt; He only is my Rock and my Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs; He is my Defence, I ſhall not utterly be moved. I will ſing of Mercy and Judgment, unto thee, O God, will I ſing. O that I had ſeen what a God I have ſinned againſt! O do not ſin againſt God, do not that abominable thing which his ſoul hateth. You cannot know his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. I ſought the Lord, and he heard me. God is in this Town: God is amongst his People, he hath heard your prayers: tell them he hath heard them for me. Now I would not live if I might: I hope I ſhould not be flattered: I would fain have lived that I might have honoured God, whom I have diſhonoured, but he knows what I am, and what I ſhould be, better than I do. Blind that I was, to ſin againſt ſuch a God, to do that which his ſoul hateth. <hi>He was all this while in ſuch a deep rapture of joy, and ſpoke with ſuch force, as though his heart would have come out to have ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Chains being almoſt off, theſe were
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105482:17"/>ſome of his expreſſions;</hi> O happy Chains, that held me till I had the Favour of God! I would have over-run thine hand, but I could not if I would; O the Patience of God! O boundleſs Mercy to ſuch a wretch as I; an Iron Heart and Iron Chains gone together; O boundleſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limitable Mercy! What ſhall I do for God? O that I could honour God! <hi>Parting with his Wife, he thus expreſt himſelf;</hi> Poor Wife I have nothing to leave thee, but O that thou mayeſt have the loving Favour of God, any thing, any thing with the Loving-Favour of God. We did not honour God with what He gave us, but lived unthankfully, and unquietly; we ſinned againſt God with his own Mercies: Why ſhould they live together unthankfully and unquietly, and ſin againſt me with mine own Mercies? Part them, part them: O how juſt is it that we ſhould be parted! <hi>Seeing his Relations, he thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to pity them;</hi> O poor wretches that muſt be left to ſtruggle with this ſinful world, full of ſnares on every ſide, my heart pitties you; O poor wretches I am afraid to think how you ſhould get through the Snares round about you; Lord keep you by his Mighty Power through Faith unto Salvation. What a ſtir doth the Devil and the World make to deſtroy one poor ſoule? your very griefs are folly in respect of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not long after being alone, his Brother
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105482:17"/>and Siſter went to him, who found him ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down with his eyes ſhut, his face look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yellow, and his countenance as if he had not been the ſame man: They asked him how it was with him; and told him that God had put away his ſins and would never look at them any more, and that it was the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil that threw his ſins in his face; but he anſwered;</hi> All is gone now, I am in the dark, I cannot ſee which is the way, but I would hope againſt hope; <hi>And again he ſaid,</hi> Though He kill me, yet will I truſt in him. <hi>Some of the ſtanders-by told him that the Devil would do the worſt he could againſt him, Becauſe he loved God and hated ſin, and would fain deſtroy the kingdom of the Devil, but Jeſus Chriſt hath prayed for him that his Faith fail not: They mentioned that Scripture alſo where it is ſaid,</hi> When the Enemy ſhall come in like a Flood, the Spirit of the Lord ſhall lift up a Standard againſt him, <hi>which Scripture much refreſhed him. Then ſaid he,</hi> Theſe are comfortable Scriptures indeed, Lord keep me from Temptation, ſuffer me not to be tempted above what I am able; Keep me by thy mighty Power through Faith unto Salvation. <hi>And being come to his former Rapture of Joy, thus he expreſt it;</hi> Juſtice and Mercy are met together, Righteouſneſs and Peace have kiſſed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105482:18"/>each other, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs and Peace to my poor Soul. <hi>He began again to pitty us who were left behind, and ſaid,</hi> I am glad to dye, becauſe I ſhall be freed from ſin; and glad to dye, becauſe ſin ſhall be ſhamed; I ſhall have the ſame nature about me if I live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As he was going towards the Execution, thus he ſaid;</hi> Thou doſt not willingly afflict nor greive the children of men; if leſſer ſtrokes would have done it, this ſhould not have been: Oh how many precious Sacraments have I abuſed! Oh the Patience of God to ſuch a ſinful Creature as I! O that I could honour God, whom I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt; I would fain honour thee; Lord help me: honour thy ſelf, O Lord. <hi>Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully looking upon the multitude, he ſaid;</hi> All theſe are to ſee ſin ſhamed. <hi>When the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers bad them ſtand off him, he ſaid,</hi> O do not keep God's People from me this little moment that I am to be in this World, they are my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and my comfort. <hi>As he went, he often expreſt great admiration of God's wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, boundleſs, and unlimited Mercy to him, and an earneſt deſire of honouring God: And when ſome good People that he priz'd as thoſe that feared God, came to him as he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and expreſſed their affection, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God for him, he ſeemed to be much cheared by it, and thus he ſaid with a ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105482:18"/>countenance,</hi> I am gathered, I am ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, they have gathered me; Sin is going to be executed; our Kingdom will be the greateſt. <hi>A Friend going with him, cheared him up with the words of Dr.</hi> Taylor <hi>of</hi> Hadley, <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Martyrdom;</hi> It is but one ſtept to my Fathers Houſe; <hi>but his countenance grew very dejected and ſad thereupon, and thus he ſaid,</hi> Ah! but I am not ſuch an one: <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately growing more chearful, he ſaid,</hi> But ſome he ſaves as fire-brands out of the fire; and ſo me: In the midſt of Judgement, thou remembreſt Mercy. Will God accept of me to honour his Truth? I fain would. I hope God will help me: I ſhall honour his Truth. How truly is his Word fulfilled on me. <hi>And being come to the place of Execution, after he had kneeled down, and prayed very pertinently and well, he concluded with theſe words;</hi> Now Lord help me to honour Thee.</p>
            <p>Then he directed his Speech to the People to this purpoſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>My dear Friends and Neighbours, you are come hither not only to ſee a poor Sinner hanged, here is ſomething that is ſpiritual to be taken notice of; O that you might not let that ſlip; O that you might
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105482:19"/>not let it ſlip. Here is the truth of God's Word to be made appear upon me; <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall fail, but not one jot of God's Word ſhall fail, but ſhall all be fulfilled.</hi> The truth of God's Word will be made good up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all you that are here preſent, ſooner or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And firſt let me tell you, how true it hath been upon me. I was born of Parents that ſerved God: I had a Father that feared God, and a Mother and other Relations that are here preſent; Brothers and Siſters that ſerved God, who followed me with their counſel, and their tears; but becauſe I did not receive their good Counſel, nor follow it, I began at the length to be weary of it, and not to love it; I did not love the very houſe ſometimes, and cared not how little I came to it, becauſe I could not be quiet in it, but they would be counſelling me for my good. Oh! what ſhall I ſay? I have been a Son of many reproofs, but I hardened my neck; And how is God's Word made good upon me in this? <hi>He that being often repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and hardeneth his neck, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed.</hi> My ſin hath alwayes been running from Counſel; for had I hearkened to faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Counſel, and followed that, it had been otherwiſe with me, I think; and juſt it was with God that I ſhould be taken, in running
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105482:19"/>away from Counſel: For I think if my wife had not bidden me ſtay within, I ſhould not have gone out; but becauſe ſhe bad me, and I having a readineſs to do contrary, out I went, and ſome ſuch words as theſe I uſed to my wife; <hi>Doſt thou think that I will be afraid to go about my buſineſs for fear of an Apprentice-boy!</hi> I was no ſooner out, but I knew I had done ill, and had a mind to go in, but I had no power then, I ſhould have ſtopt ſooner. O let every one hearken to Counſel. I had an aptneſs to do contrary, and ſo I was left to my ſelf, that if I needs would run from Counſel, I might ſee what would come of it, and ſee whither it brought me. O let every one take heed of ſin, ſtop ſin in the beginning, for you cannot ſtop when you will, if once you give way to ſin. When my Mother or ſome others would deal faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with me, I did for the moſt part believe that they ſpake to me out of true love, and could ſee it to be right counſel, and ſuch as I had need of, and yet there was that in me that put me upon doing contrary; though I thought it was ſuch as I had great need of, and that which I thought I would ſure fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, yet there was that in me that did not love it, and would rather have been without it: And although I longed for Sabbath days,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105482:20"/>and loved them when they were come, and delighted to hear good Sermons, and was thereby convinced of ſome things that were then amiſs in me, and ſhould then purpoſe againſt them; ſo that I ſhould think it would ſure be otherwiſe; yet when Monday came, and I was as it were turned into the world again, I was the ſame as before, as though I had never purpoſed or been convinced: for if any one had but called me, I muſt needs go, and though there was that in me, that did reſiſt, and would have hindered me, and the victory ſhould have been on God's ſide, yet it ſeldom was, but was for the moſt part ſtill born down. The victory ſhould have been on God's ſide and his Words ſide: my reſolutions ſhould have held me; and though God's Word and my reſolutions would hold me ſometimes, and for a great while, yet at the laſt I ſhould break through all, though they were ſtrong bonds, ſuch as I thought I never durſt nor would break over: yet after a while, when I thought I was ſafe, if one that I had uſed to go with, had but come to my ſhop, I muſt preſently go with him; that which before held me, would then ſeem lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and I could then break through it all eaſily; and thus I loved a little Ale bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than God, and better than his Word.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105482:20"/>Take heed of Company, and loving Ale too well, for there is more evil in it, than you are aware of; for when I had kept my ſelf from that, I was like another man; but when I had taken too much of that, it would take al fear from me, ſo that I ſhould not care what I ſaid or did, my tongue would then run at no gage. I had an aptneſs alwayes to ſpeak untruths, but ſpecially at ſuch times. I was a man full of words; and can a man full of words be juſtified? <hi>In the multitude of words there wants not iniquity.</hi> O that good creature that I abuſed by pouring in too much of, and made my ſelf unfit to do any thing that was good by it: if ſome poor body that wanted it, had had ſome of that, which I might have ſpared, and have been better without, it would have made their heart glad, they would have bleſſed God for it, and God ſhould have had honour by it: but I did not ſo, my belly devoured all: <hi>Meat is for the belly, and the belly for meat, but God ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both it and them.</hi> I was full of Ale when this fell out that I am brought hither for; Ale had made me fearleſs and confident, or elſe I ſhould have been afraid, and careful to have kept out of their way, as at other times; that fear which ſhould then have kept me, was then wanting: O ſure if I had known
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105482:21"/>what would have followed, and that I ſhould have done ſuch a thing, I ſhould have been afraid of every cup, and nothing could have forced me to have taken more than was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: but though I did not know what would follow, yet I might have been afraid: for what may not a man do when he is not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but is fearleſs, and hath not his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding about him? Oh, no life is ſafe, but a fearing, watching, ſelf-denying life; let me ſay this again, No life but a <hi>fearing, watching, ſelf-denying life,</hi> is a ſafe life. And as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this young-man, I had no more thoughts or intention to kill him, then I had to kill mine own brother; and when any one would ſpeak to me to take heed leſt any ſuch thing ſhould follow, I ſhould diſdain in my heart that any one ſhould have ſuch thoughts of me, as once to fear leſt I ſhould kill any one, for my nature, I thought, could never be ſo cruel; and again I thought that I had knowledge, and that I, of any one in the Town, ſhould never commit that ſin, becauſe I knew more againſt it than many others did, I thought, and had better education; but I ſhould have been afraid of my ſelf, and was not; <hi>I hid my ſins, and therefore did not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per:</hi> How true is God's Word made good upon me in this thing alſo: for I alwayes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105482:21"/>ſought the favour of men, and if I ſhould but have had that, I ſhould have looked no further, but have ſate down contented with it, yet it alwayes fled from me: I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpoken that which was not ſo, when I thought it might further that deſign; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that very thing, wherein I went out of my way, and did evil, thinking to gain more favour thereby, was uſually a means to make me loſe that favour, and room in their hearts, which I had before: But it was better for me that I had it not; for if I could have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten men to think well of me, I think I ſhould have thought well of my ſelf, and ſhould have ſitten down contented without looking any further. God ordered it otherwiſe for me, and it was better for me, bleſſed be God: and was not I met with in this, for had I the favour of men? had I? you all know how it hath been. But O why ſhould I ſpeak? God is juſt, very juſt: for Oh what a life have I lived; ſure if I were to live again, I would not live as I have done: but I had time, and I did not improve it: I ſhould have honoured God with that precious time that he gave me, but I did not, but ſought the favour of men with it, and ſinned againſt God with it: I did not make that uſe of my time that it was given me for, and becauſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105482:22"/>I did not, therefore I muſt have no more; I had time once, but whilſt I had it, I lived to my ſelf with it. God gave it me, but I did not honour him with it who gave it me, but other things had my time, and other things had my heart; and ſince I made ſuch uſe of it, Why ſhould I have any more? I muſt have no more; I brought forth fruit to my felf: an empty Vine: God gave me time that I might lay it out as he would have me, but I did not: a fruitleſs tree: <hi>Cut it down, why cumbreth it the ground any longer?</hi> O you that have time before you yet, prize it, and improve it, for it will not laſt alwayes: do not loſe one jot of it, by idling it away and by ſinning it away; all the time you have is little enough to do that work which God hath given you to do in it. I had time but now I muſt have no more, and your time, will be gone ſhortly.</p>
               <p>O let no body preſume becauſe of me, for one of a thouſand is not ſnatcht out of the jaws of the Devil as I am: O what ſhall I ſay! for the Lord's ſake take heed of ſin; O do not that abominable thing that his Soul hateth. If his Children tranſgreſs and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his Way, <hi>He will viſit their iniquity with the Rod.</hi> Believe me for I am a dying man, the truth of God's Word will be made good
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105482:22"/>upon all ſooner or later; what he ſpake with his Mouth he hath fulfilled with his Hand, as you will ſee upon me this day. I being often reproved hardned my neck, and now I muſt ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy as to my body; but to the honour of his Mercy I have hope in him: He hath forgiven me my great debt: Foraſmuch as I had nothing to pay, thou forgaveſt the debt: O unlimited Mercy, what a God art thou, that when all refuge failed and I had no whither elſe to go, that then thou ſhouldeſt accept of me, when I was caſt out even to the loathing of my perſon: O bleſſed be thy Name for ever: O that I had known thee better and ſerved thee better! O what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of forgiveneſs muſt I be ſaved by? Mighty Forgiveneſs, Lord help me to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give as I would be forgiven. If any of you here preſent did plot or contrive that which is now come to paſs, the taking away of my life, I do freely forgive you, and I would have you pray unto God that he would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give you, that ſo it may be forgiven, and may never come againſt you. And now Lord I come unto thee: I am a ſinful crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but pardon and accept of me. I have broken all thy holy Laws and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: I have done as much evil as I could
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105482:23"/>have done againſt thee; but I come unto thee, pardon and accept of me for Jeſus ſake: I have no whither elſe to fly, accept of me for Chriſt's ſake; for Chriſt's ſake: Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit; Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit.</p>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce it hath pleaſed God to make known unto you, by his Providence upon this young man, a freſh diſcovery of his great forgiveneſs, and alſo his Severity againſt ſin: And ſince it is the will of God that none of his Providences ſhould be ſlighted, or return in vain; let you and I in the Fear of God take heed that it may not be in vain unto us. We may clearly ſee by the Word of God, and by this and many other his Providences to the Sons of men, that he is a Merciful, and yet a Juſt God: Merciful our God was unto this young man, in that he followed him with many awakings, many convictions, many good purpoſes, reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deſires, and yet Juſt in puniſhing him for the abuſe of theſe his Mercies, Juſt in letting his own iniquity take him, and bind him over to puniſhment; And won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Merciful unto him in bringing good
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105482:23"/>unto him out of his evil. You and I, it may be, have through the Mercies of God unto us ſeveral convictions, good purpoſes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, ſome good affections and deſires of being better; but what fruit comes of them? do we not bear them down, and are we not ſtill the ſame men as formerly? Let us fear before God, for he is a Juſt God. All are not tempted alike to the ſame ſins; ſome are tempted one way, ſome another way: ſome Peoples ſins are open, others ſecret; Let us therefore ſeriouſly conſider what our ſins are before God; they may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of great agravations; Let us conſider of them, and by this example of Repentance, let us be ſtired up to Repentance, and a more diligent ſeeking after God, that ſo his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be prevented. And ſince there may be (as we have ſeen in this our Friend) many convictions, good affections, deſires and purpoſes, and yet groſs ſins, ſuch as may provoke the face of God againſt us, let us conſider of it, and fear and be ſtirred up thereby to beg of God that we may not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke Him as he did, not take boldneſs to ſin, in expectation of Mercy at laſt; Let none preſume becauſe of him, for few are ſnatcht out of the jaws of the Devil as he was; but obey the Motions of God's holy Spirit, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105482:24"/>by it we may be able to overcome all our Spiritual enemies.</p>
               <p>And ſince we who are his relations fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may, and are obliged to give God the honour of his Goodneſs and his Truth in hearing Prayers, and having received upon this our Friend a freſh occaſion of the ſame; therefore, to this end you may further take notice by that which followeth, ſomething that may make it appear that God is a God of Truth and heareth Prayers. He was a ſon of many Prayers; I will inſtance only in one of his relations, a Siſter of his who is dead, whom God made eminent in Grace, and a bleſſing to the Family wherein ſhe was: who while ſhe lived, carried him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her heart, ſtriving with God by prayer for him, and by faithful counſel and reproofs with him concerning his ſpiritual conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for ſometimes ſhe would with tears of kindneſs, kiſſing him, and weeping upon him, entreat him to conſider of his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and would make it plain to him accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture, that his condition was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſad, and that either it muſt not be the Word of God, or elſe he muſt be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, if ever he had any ſaving intereſt in it. Sometimes ſhe would tell him (and that truly) that ſhe had not ſlept all night,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105482:24"/>becauſe of him, ſhe was ſo full of fearfull thoughts concerning him, leſt he ſhould be ſnatch'd away by death in his preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which muſt then certainly be ſad. Thus ſhe continued ſeveral years, as oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and his condition received, ſeveral wayes to deal faithfully with him; and one night, as we well remember, after ſhe had been perſwading him to ſtay in the houſe, and reade to her, and not go out into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany as formerly he uſed; and telling him, that if he would but deny himſelf and ſtay, he ſhould find better comfort and delight, than any he could meet with in his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, with many other motives and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions ſhe uſed, as though ſhe would needs prevail with him, But when ſhe ſaw that ſhe could not, and that he would go notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as he went from her, theſe words ſhe ſpake to him; <hi>Brother, wilt thou go notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all that I can ſay; well, thou wilt not hear me, but I hope God will; and that ſometime before thou dyeſt, thou ſhalt have little comfort any where but in God's Word, and well if thou mayeſt have it there.</hi> By theſe words you may perceive ſhe was earneſt in prayer for him, and that though ſhe could not prevail with her Brother, yet ſhe hoped to prevail with God for him: and upon her death-bed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105482:25"/>ſhe ſpake theſe words following to ſome of her relations then by, to the end ſhe might encourage them to ſeek unto God. <hi>I never</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>was earneſtly ſet to beg any thing of God, that I durſt pray abſolutly for, that I was denied; and I have ſome hope concerning</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <hi>that poor Lad, that there are ſome prayers put up for him that will not be denied, which will not depart until the Moſt High give heed thereunto.</hi> And although ſhe dyed in Faith, and did not in her life time ſee that change which ſhe hoped for, yet God, who never faileth thoſe that put their truſt in him, did not fail her, but heard her prayers in his own due time, and in his own way: We therefore who are hereby obliged, do on her behalf, and on our own, deſire to ſpeak good of God; for we have largely experienced upon our ſelves, and upon theſe our relations that it is not in vain to ſeek unto the Almighty; for as we have heard, ſo have we ſeen it made good; Such as ſate in darkneſs and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, being bound in afflictions and irons, becauſe they rebelled againſt the Lord and contemned his Counſels, yet even then when they cryed unto the Lord, He heard them, and ſaved them out of their diſtreſs. O that men would Praiſe the Lord with us for this his Goodneſs, and for his wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105482:25"/>works to the ſons of men: for he ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the hungry ſoul with good things; he fulfilleth the deſire of ſuch as fear him and hope in his Mercies. Be encouraged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be earneſt in ſeeking unto God for your ſelves and for your relations; for the faithful prayer of a Righteous man availeth much if it be fervent; he that asketh recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, and he that ſeeketh findeth, and to him that knocketh it ſhall be opened; and as <hi>David experienced,</hi> even ſo may we, that the Word of the Lord is a tryed Word, and all his! Judgments are done in truth; And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſeeming ſad Providences which accompanied this Mercy may ſeem to leſſen it in the eyes of ſome, yet let it not, for God's Wayes are not as our wayes, nor his Thoughts as our thoughts. And though ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man came off with ſhame in this Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, yet both the Goodneſs and Severity of God were hereby made to appear: Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that ſo ſin might not be encouraged, and Goodneſs that ſo we might be encouraged to ſeek unto God, and therefore this death was the beſt and the beſt for him, and doth not leſſen the Mercy.</p>
               <p>And ſince laying open the Vertues of others, ſometimes hath and may be as a whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, putting an edge upon the Graces of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105482:26"/>others, drawing on and encouraging them to imitate the ſame; it therefore will not be amiſs, ſince ſhe of whom we ſpake is out of the reach of being hurt by applauſe, to give you further knowledge concerning her: She was of a courteous winning carriage, very diligent in her buſineſs, and a careful at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender upon all the Ordinances of God. She was a faithful friend unto whomſoever ſhe was acquainted withall; for if ſhe knew them to be accuſtomed in any evil, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhe thought to be their fault of faults, ſhe would be ſure to tell them of it, and yet in ſuch a way, that they could not chuſe but ſee her true love to them thereby: And this conſideration, as ſhe ſaid, ſometimes put her upon this duty, <hi>viz. What if I muſt never ſee this Friend of mine again until I meet him in Eternity, ſince I think ſuch and ſuch things to be his fault, if I do not ſeriouſly tell him of it, if he miſcary, how ſhall I then anſwer it? how ſhal I look him in the face? may he not then curſe me?</hi> She alſo accuſtomed herſelf to walk out in the evening, when it began to grow dark, into ſome ſolitary place, as the Church-yard where people are buried, or without the wals of the Town by the Water-ſide; and being asked by ſome of her relations, why ſhe choſe ſuch a time, and ſuch a ſolitary place? ſhe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105482:26"/>anſwered thus: <hi>Becauſe I can at ſuch a time, or in ſuch a place, the better put my ſelf into a dying condition; for when the fears of the night are about me, and the fleſh apprehends ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then I can ſee the things of the world to be as they are, &amp; can think thus with my ſelf: What if I muſt never have to do with anything in the world more? I muſt ſhortly be in the condition of theſe dead perſons under me, and my place muſt know me no more: and when all the world is gone with me, what is it that will abide or ſtand me in ſtead at ſuch a time? And likewiſe my conſcience would at ſuch times bring to my mind ſuch things which I had done, or ſaid, or thought evil in, which before paſſed without taking notice of. And theſe thoughts are of uſe to further me in ſeeking after that, wherein I then found ſolid comfort, and to make me more watchful againſt ſuch things as at ſuch times I found my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be offended withal: I find likewiſe that I can be more free from diſtracting thoughts; Though I cannot ſay I am altogether free from natural fear at ſuch a time, yet after a while when I have, by acting Faith, overcome it, and reaſoned away my fear; then I find great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, great delight, and ſatisfaction in God, and am thereby encouraged chearfully to go through thoſe tryals and duties which otherwiſe in my place I found hard.</hi> And one time as ſhe was
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105482:27"/>ſtealing forth, as formerly, to her ſolitary walk, her Mother perceiving, ſeemed to be angry, that ſhe ſhould go out at ſuch a time of night to endanger her health; but ſhe anſwered her, and that almoſt with tears; <hi>Good Mother, do not hinder me of my portion: it is my portion in this world, neither can I undergo any buſineſs, or go through the world as I ought, without ſome ſuch refreſhments.</hi> Further, if any one had taken offence at her, though cauſleſly, ſhe would be the firſt in ſeeking reconciliation, and ſeldom or never without good ſucceſs: and when ſhe met with any deriding ſpeeches, or backbiting from others, inſtead of repaying home in the ſame kind, ſhe would overcome their evil with good. This was uſually her word; <hi>What is my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? what would God have me to do in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi> and ſo ſhe practiſed; for ſhe would uſually go or write to ſuch perſons, and deal in ſuch a manner, and ſhew ſuch meekneſs, that either ſhe gained them to be her friends, or elſe their mouthes were by this her carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age ſo ſtopt, that they could not faſten their reproaches upon her.</p>
               <p>I might make a large diſcourſe concerning her, but I forbear.— She was buried the tenth day of <hi>February, Anno Domini</hi> 1658. The place of Scripture ſhe choſe to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105482:27"/>upon at her Funeral, was <hi>John</hi> 12.26. <hi>[If any man ſerve me, let him follow me; and where I am, there ſhall alſo my ſervant be: If any man ſerve me, him will my Father honour.]</hi> Which (as ſhe ſaid) ſhe could ſcarce ever reade, but it would affect her, ſo as to cauſe tears.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Here follow alſo ſome Verſes, made by the ſame <hi>Mary Barton,</hi> in the praiſe of <hi>CHARITY:</hi> She her ſelf being ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular in the love and practice of this Grace, above moſt others. The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of them is taken out of the 13th Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe matchleſs <hi>Worth</hi> of Charity,</l>
                  <l>my heart deſires to prize;</l>
                  <l>O that in all I do or ſay,</l>
                  <l>I may with it adviſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If I the Tongue of Angels had,</l>
                  <l>or of men moſt renown'd</l>
                  <l>For Eloquence, which makes men glad</l>
                  <l>more than ſweet Muſicks ſound:</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:105482:28"/>
                  <l>Yet void of this, there would in me</l>
                  <l>of worth no more appear,</l>
                  <l>Then ſounding Braſs, or Cymbals have</l>
                  <l>that tinkle to our ear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though I through gifts of Prophecy,</l>
                  <l>could things to come foretell,</l>
                  <l>Or though in underſtanding, I</l>
                  <l>all others did excel:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though I deep Myſt'ries could unfold,</l>
                  <l>or did ſuch Faith enjoy,</l>
                  <l>That I could Mountains high remove,</l>
                  <l>when they did me annoy:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet void of this, ſo prime a Grace,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould accounted be,</l>
                  <l>As nothing by him, who all hearts</l>
                  <l>doth plainly ſearch and ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though all my Goods unto the poor,</l>
                  <l>I do moſt freely give,</l>
                  <l>Or unto ſcorching flames commit</l>
                  <l>this fleſh wherein I live:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet void of this, it cannot help,</l>
                  <l>or any whit amount,</l>
                  <l>To profit me when I appear</l>
                  <l>in day of mine account.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:105482:28"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Seeing its abſence makes all vain,</l>
                  <l>its preſence then is bliſs.</l>
                  <l>Therefore give ear, and you ſhall hear,</l>
                  <l>what this chief Vertue is.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It's <hi>Charity</hi> that ſuffers long,</l>
                  <l>and kind hath ever been.</l>
                  <l>She envies not, nor vaunts her ſelf,</l>
                  <l>puft up was never ſeen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Unſeemly rude behaviour,</l>
                  <l>ſhe alwayes doth deteſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeking not her own, is ſtill</l>
                  <l>poſſeſt with inward reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She thinks no evil, nor her joy,</l>
                  <l>in wickedneſs hath ſet,</l>
                  <l>But evermore made glad by Truth,</l>
                  <l>ſeeks Truth not to forget.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By Patience ſhe can all things bear,</l>
                  <l>That here on Earth befal;</l>
                  <l>Upheld by Faith, by Hope made glad;</l>
                  <l>ſhe well endureth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Excellency more it hath,</l>
                  <l>it ever ſtill abides,</l>
                  <l>And in that breaſt where ere its wrought,</l>
                  <l>for aye it there reſides.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:105482:29"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor is that ſentence doom'd on her</l>
                  <l>which on ſome Gifts is paſt,</l>
                  <l>That they ſhall fail, yea ceaſe and quite</l>
                  <l>be done away at laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now but in part our knowledge is,</l>
                  <l>In part we propheſie,</l>
                  <l>But when Perfection we attain,</l>
                  <l>This done away ſhall be:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Even as we ſee that men of years</l>
                  <l>thoſe rudiments forſake,</l>
                  <l>Of which whilſt children in their youth</l>
                  <l>they great account did make.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For now the perfect'ſt views we have</l>
                  <l>are dark as in a glaſs,</l>
                  <l>But then our perfect ſight ſhall be</l>
                  <l>as when face anſwers face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whil'ſt we are here in our warfare</l>
                  <l>by Faith we ſtand our ground,</l>
                  <l>And are by hope kept up that we</l>
                  <l>with waves are not quite drown'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But <hi>Charity</hi> of all theſe three</l>
                  <l>in honour doth ſurmount,</l>
                  <l>And he that makes moſt uſe of it</l>
                  <l>ſhall beſt give his account.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
